Finding aid to Office of the Acting President Elizabeth Morrow files CA.MS.00012
Smith College Archives
Office of the Acting President Elizabeth Morrow files
1939-1940
Smith College Archives
Morrow, Elizabeth, 1873-1955.
CA.MS.00012
1.042 linear feet (4 containers)
Elizabeth Cutter Morrow served as Smith's acting president. She was also a Smith alumna, a teacher, author, volunteer, and trustee. This collection contains correspondence, news clippings, photographs, presidential documents, speeches, reports and other materials. Correspondents include the Neilson family and the Davis family.
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth Reeve Cutter Morrow has been called Smith's most outstanding alumna. Born in Cleveland, Ohio in 1873, Elizabeth Cutter was the daughter of Charles Long Cutter and Annie E. (Spencer) Cutter. Her father was Secretary General of L. and Wheeling Railroad. Having received her early education in Cleveland at Miss Mittleberger's School, she was later granted a B. L. degree from Smith College in the Class of 1896. She studied at the Sorbonne in Paris, France from 1896 to 1897 as well as in Florence, Italy.
In 1903 Elizabeth Reeve Cutter married Dwight Whitney Morrow. Dwight Morrow, born in Huntington, W.V. in 1873, graduated from Amherst College in 1896. He served as the United States Ambassador to Mexico from 1927 - 1930, during the Hoover administration, and served in the United States Senate from 1930 until his death on October 5, 1931. They had four children: Elizabeth Reeve, Anne Spencer, Dwight Whitney, and Constance Cutter. All three daughters attended Smith College. Elizabeth Cutter Morrow was the grandmother of twelve, including the famous Lindbergh baby, son of Anne Spencer and her husband Col. Charles A. Lindbergh.
Elizabeth Cutter Morrow was the recipient of honorary degrees from six leading colleges and universities including: Amherst College, 1933; New Jersey College for Women, 1935; Smith College, 1937; New York University, 1940; Lafayette College,1940; and Princeton, 1940. Described by Dr. William Allen Neilson in conferring the degree of Doctor of Humane letters upon her in 1937, "President of the Alumnae Association, and for sixteen years Trustee of Smith College, author of distinction in prose and verse, the multitude of whose services to her college and her country - far greater than the world knows - makes it impossible to describe adequately the alumna who has earned in most abundant measure our love, our honor, and our gratitude.
Taking an active role in the life and well-being of her alma mater, Elizabeth Cutter Morrow was president of the Smith College Alumnae Association from 1917 - 1920. She was a member of the War Services Board which directed Smith College relief units overseas. Between 1920 - 1926 she was the Alumnae representative to the Board of Trustees, and later, in 1926, was elected a Trustee by the Board. Her largest contribution, however, was her role as acting president for the interim year, 1939 - 1940, after the resignation of William Neilson as president in 1939.
Elizabeth Cutter Morrow was not a professional woman whose "field" can be easily described. She certainly achieved eminence in education, philanthropy, finance, and literature. She was a teacher of English, History, and French in private schools before her marriage to Dwight Whitney Morrow in 1903. During her marriage she published prose and verse in many popular magazines, as well as publishing multiple children's books, including The Painted Pig, Quatrains for My Daughter, The Rabbit's Nest, Shannon, A Pint of Judgment and Casa Manana, which was chosen as one of 150 of the most beautiful books between 1931 and 1933.
Elizabeth Cutter Morrow was active in local as well as national and international affairs. She was chairman of the Community Chest when it was first organized in Englewood, New Jersey, the town she called home. She was also involved in her local church, Women's Club, Memorial House (civic center) and was even chairman of the Board of The Little School in Englewood, founded by her daughter Elizabeth. She was a member of the executive committee of the New York National War Fund Committee. She was one of the founders for Food for Freedom Inc. Morrow was the first woman to serve on the Board of the Union Theological Seminary and was a member of the National Board of the Y. W. C. A., where she took a leading role in its fund raising campaigns. Elizabeth Cutter Morrow played an important role in issues abroad. During her husband's time as ambassador to Mexico, 1927-31930, she supported him in his resolve to strengthen relations between Mexico and the United States. Morrow was also an honorary vice-president of the American Association for the United Nations, Inc.
On January 23, 1955 she died at the age of eighty-two. In an address at the Smith College memorial service Ada Comstock Notestein, former dean and trustee of Smith College, as well as former president of Radcliffe College, said: "...She was one of those rare beings for whose courage nothing is too great, and for whose imagination nothing is too small...She was a benefactor and philanthropist without any apparent consciousness of doing more than anyone would have done in her place."
Scope and Contents
The Office of the Acting President Elizabeth Morrow files document her official duties as acting president of Smith College. The collection includes correspondence, news clippings, photographs, presidential documents, speeches, and reports. An important aspect of the collection is the information concerning the Special Committee on Choosing a President and Trustee.
The collection documents Morrow's achievements and her involvement with Smith College. Among other things the collection highlights academic departments and Interdepartmental majors, the restoration of the President's Office, and documents events such as Rally Day and Commencement.
Correspondence consists of letters to and from Elizabeth Morrow concerning matters of the President, letters to and from the Neilson family, and letters to and from the Davis family.
Arrangement
The bulk of the material is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Related Materials
Elizabeth Morrow Personal papers, 1892-1947
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Office of the Acting President Elizabeth Morrow Files were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in the Smith College Archives are open for use, with the following exceptions:
Faculty tenure and promotion files, as well as inactive faculty files are closed permanently. Board of Trustees' records are closed permanently. Minutes of the Faculty Council are closed to all except current Smith College Faculty for a period of 75 years following their creation. Student academic records, student disciplinary records, and all records containing FERPA-covered student information are closed during the lifetime of the student. Student records created 100 years or more ago are assumed to be about deceased students. In all cases, the College Archives will continue to provide public access to materials that were intended to be public at the time of their creation (press releases, publications, etc.)
Smith College -- presidents; Morrow, Elizabeth, 1873-1955.; Smith College--Presidents.; Neilson, William Allan, 1869-1946.; Davis, Herbert John, 1893-1967.; Smith College. Office of President.
- A, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.1, Folder 1)
  - Academic Departments and Interdepartmental Programs: A-F, 1939-40 (Box 446.1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Departments and Interdepartmental Programs: G-M, 1939-40 (Box 446.1, Folder 3)
  - Academic Departments and Interdepartmental Programs: P-Z, 1939-40 (Box 446.1, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae Association, 1939-40 (Box 446.1, Folder 5)
  - Alumnae Clubs, 1939-40 (Box 446.1, Folder 6)
  - Archives, 1939-40 (Box 446.1, Folder 7)
- B, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.1, Folder 8)
  - Buildings and Grounds: President's Office Restoration, 1939-40 (Box 446.1, Folder 9)
- C, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.1, Folder 10)
  - Cambridge School, 1939-40 (Box 446.1, Folder 11)
  - Commencement, 1940 (Box 446.1, Folder 12)
  - Committee on Resources, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 1)
- D-E, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 2)
  - Davis, Herbert & Gladys, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 3)
  - Davis, Herbert J.: Inauguration of President, 1940 (Box 446.2, Folder 4)
- F-G, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Letter to Elizabeth Cutter Morrow, 1940 (Box 446.2, Folder 6)
- H, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 7)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 8)
  - Houses, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 9)
- I-J, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 10)
- K-L, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 11)
  - The Lees, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 12)
  - Library, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 13)
- M, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 15)
  - Museum of Art, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 16)
- N, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 17)
  - Neilson, William Allen, Elizabeth & Margaret, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 18)
  - Notebook, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 19)
- O-P, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 20)
  - Plans for Refugee Children, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 21)
  - President's Report, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 22)
- R, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 23)
  - Rally Day, 1940 (Box 446.2, Folder 24)
- S, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.2, Folder 25)
  - Scholarships, 1939-40 (Box 446.2, Folder 26)
  - Secretary to the President, 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 1)
  - Seven Women's Colleges: Annual Congress, 1939 (Box 446.3, Folder 2)
  - Special Committee on Choosing a President, 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 3)
  - Speeches at Smith College, 1939 (Box 446.3, Folder 4)
  - Speeches at Smith College, 1940 (Box 446.3, Folder 5)
- T-U, 1939-40; n. d. (Box 446.3, Folder 6)
  - Trustees: Corbett, Elliot R., 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 7)
  - Trustees: Dalrymple, John S., 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 8)
  - Trustees: Emerson, Kendall, 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 9)
  - Trustees: Gleason, Hollis T., 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 10)
  - Trustees: Hofer, Philip, 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 11)
  - Trustees: Huntington, W. Chapin, 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 12)
  - Trustees: Jones, Frederic M., 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 13)
  - Trustees: Oldham, John E., 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 14)
  - Trustees: Raymond, Eleanor, 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 15)
  - Trustees: Smith, Frank C., 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 16)
  - Trustees: Stevenson, George S., 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 17)
  - Trustees: Teagle, Frank, 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 18)
  - Trustees: Valentine, Alan, 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 19)
- V-Z, 1939-40 (Box 446.3, Folder 20)
- Books
  - My Favorite Age, 1939 (Box 446.4)